Hi. Next, I'm going to talk about what makes a good bulb bad the good, bad and the ugly when it comes to flower bulbs.
There are a lot of things that can happen to your bulbs when they're stored. I found bulbs under a table three years later, it was a Calla Lily bulb, and I planted it in the summertime and it came right up and bloomed beautifully.
I've bought Tulips, put them in a plastic bag and threw them in the back of the trunk for a couple of weeks and they came out this moldy, mushy mess.
So, there are some problems that you can have with bulbs but there are easy solutions.
And I always treat gardening like throwing a party.
You invite all the plants over; some of them show up looking beautiful and good moods and having a good time, others show up just a mess.
So, you enjoy their company while they're here and not take it personally, and there are always more bulbs that you can purchase.
So, mold is not a flower bulb's best friend.
And mold happens when they get too wet, and so it's part of like they're decaying or rotting process.
This is a peony root that got wet at the farmers market and you can tell it has just got mold all over it.
But there is a silver lining. Most people would say, "I'm throwing it away. It's got mold on it," but look, there's an eye right here on it and it's still good.
So, if you threw it away you're losing a $10-plant. Even if one of the eyes here is soft and mushy, it's no good.
So, what I just do--see? It's still fleshy like a potato. I just rip this off 'cause it's the eyes that matter, not the roots and get rid of that and you still have a good plant.
So, there's no need to always throw away every single plant you have just because there's little bit of mold. Mold is not the end of the world.
You can always put a little bit of bleach water on it or you can even dirt. I just rub a little bit of dirt on some moldy spots and all of a sudden, the bulb seems fine and the bulb itself is not damaged, it's just the covering.
For example--let's see, I've got a Tulip here and it's got a little bit of a moldy spot but if I rub some dirt on it, it seems to come right off.
So actually, if I would have went ahead and planted that, it would still be just fine. So, that doesn't always mean that the bulb is bad even if there's a little bit of mold.
Next, watch our segment number two on what to do with moldy flower bulbs.